Guide to the Chard Powers Smith Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, circa 1922-1956, undated; Series II; 50.88; (124 boxes)
  - Drama, circa 1922-1923, undated
    - Cain, notes, circa 1923 (Box 175, Folder 5651-5675)
    - Cain and The Death of Cain, drafts, circa 1923 (Box 175, Folder 5676-5702)
    - Circles, scenario draft, 1922 (Box 175, Folder 5703)
    - Experiment in Love, drafts, undated (Box 175, Folder 5704-5705)
    - Kintheon and Stor, draft, undated (Box 175, Folder 5706)
    - Puritan Children, draft, undated (Box 175, Folder 5707)
    - Rome, draft, undated (Box 175, Folder 5708)
    - Savonarola, manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 175, Folder 5709-5710)
  - Writings of others
    - Prose, circa 1926-1948, undated
      - Beabe, Dick. "The Evolution of a Preacher", undated (Box 176, Folder 5711)
      - Blair, Janet M. "A Personal Experience of Death", undated (Box 176, Folder 5712)
      - Clark, Eddie. Untitled typescript, 1941 (Box 176, Folder 5713)
      - Clay, George. Dramatizations of Taste, by Roald Dahl, Do You Like It Here, by John O'Hara, and The Hour of Letdown, by E. B. White. Typescript drafts, undated (Box 176, Folder 5714)
      - Clay, George. "Flyability", undated (Box 176, Folder 5715)
      - Cohen, Rose. "Sacred Images", circa 1925 (Box 176, Folder 5716)
      - Conant, Isabel Fiske. Typescript review of Turn of the Dial by Chard Powers Smith, undated (Box 176, Folder 5717)
      - DuBois, Rachel Davis. "What Is Cultural Democracy?", undated (Box 176, Folder 5718)
      - Ennis, William Jr. et al. Fame Field, 1948 (Box 176, Folder 5719)
      - Jeffers, Robinson. Manuscript note regarding E. A. Robinson, undated (Box 176, Folder 5720)
      - Jorgensen, Pamela. "Fish and Tails", undated (Box 176, Folder 5721)
      - Montague, R. W. "On Life", undated (Box 176, Folder 5722)
    - Poetry, undated
      - Clark, Nathaniel, undated (Box 176, Folder 5723)
      - Collins, Mike, undated (Box 176, Folder 5724)
      - Conant, Isabel Fiske, undated (Box 176, Folder 5725)
      - Cook, Julia A., undated (Box 176, Folder 5726)
      - Fineman, Irving, undated (Box 176, Folder 5727)
      - Hare, Montgomery, undated (Box 176, Folder 5728)
      - Huchting, Fritz, undated (Box 176, Folder 5729)
      - Morris, Tim, undated (Box 176, Folder 5730)
      - Oppenheimer, David, undated (Box 176, Folder 5731)
      - Piper, Miriam Sims, undated (Box 176, Folder 5732)
      - Ramanujan, A. K., undated (Box 176, Folder 5733)
      - Rorty, James, undated (Box 176, Folder 5734)
      - Rosenblatt, Herta, undated (Box 176, Folder 5735)
      - Salinger, Herman, undated (Box 176, Folder 5736)
      - Sheffield, Judy, undated (Box 176, Folder 5737)
      - Staley, Henry Charles, undated (Box 176, Folder 5738)
      - Stiver, Mary Weeden, undated (Box 176, Folder 5739)
      - Stoney, Louisa Cheveres, undated (Box 176, Folder 5740)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 176, Folder 5741-5765)
- Personal Papers, 1759-1977, undated; Series III; 4.59; (9 boxes)
  Arranged by format.
  Series III. Personal Papers contains address books, diaries, journals, financial and legal papers, school notebooks and other material pertaining to the personal life of Chard Powers Smith. Also present are scrapbooks documenting significant aspects of Smith's life and writing career in the 1920s; these contain reviews and other clippings, a few photographs, and correspondence including notes from John Masefield, Marianne Moore, Harriet Monroe, and other writers, as well as the attending doctor's account of Olive Smith's death. Of note among the legal papers is a 1759 deed documenting the sale of land in Dunstable, Province of New Hampshire, by Jonathan Powers to Isaac Powers.
  - Address books, undated (Box 177, Folder 5766-5767)
  - Diaries and journals, 1921-1923 (Box 177, Folder 5768-5771)
  - Diaries and journals, 1923-1954 (Box 178, Folder 5772-5775)
  - Diaries and journals, 1957-1973, undated (Box 179, Folder 5776-5780)
  - Financial papers, circa 1911-1973
    - Financial statements, account books, invoices and receipts, circa 1911-1969 (Box 180, Folder 5781-5786)
    - Royalty statements, 1928-1969 (Box 180, Folder 5787-5797)
  - Legal documents and contracts, 1759, 1925-1970 (Box 181, Folder 5798-5820)
    Includes one deed of land, dated 1759, signed by Jonathan Powers.
    Includes copyright certificates, 1925-1963.
  - Objects, undated (Box 182, Folder 5821-5827)
  - School notebooks, 1924 (Box 183, Folder 5828-5831)
  - Teaching materials, 1977, undated (Box 183, Folder 5832-5833)
  - Travel materials, circa 1954 (Box 183, Folder 5834-5839)
  - Other personal papers, undated (Box 183, Folder 5840-5874)
    Also stored in: Oversize
  - Other personal papers, undated (Box 184, Folder 5875-5909)
  - Scrapbook pages related to undergraduate activities at Yale, 1913-1916
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 184, Folder 5910)
  - Scrapbooks, 1923-1929 (Box 185)
- Family Papers, 1852-1965, undated; Series IV; 3.75; (9 boxes)
  Arranged in alphabetical order by family member. Correspondence by family members is listed separately.
  Series IV. Family Papers contains personal papers of Chard Powers Smith's family members. These include diaries and journals, other writings, financial papers, school notebooks and other personal papers of his mother, father, maternal grandmother, and his first wife. The series also includes correspondence of a broader circle of Smith's family members, with the exception of their correspondence with Smith, which is located in Series I. Material in this series chiefly documents the family's daily life in and near Watertown, New York in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, although a substantial file of letters from Edward North Smith to his father concerns his experiences at Hamilton College in the 1880s.
  - Powers, Lorinda Lamon, 1852-1916, undated
    - Diaries, 1889-1916 (Box 186, Folder 5911-5915)
    - Diaries (Box 187, Folder 5916-5918)
    - Sketches, notes and textbooks, 1852, 1889, undated (Box 187, Folder 5919-5922)
  - Smith, Alice Lamon Powers, 1890-1896, undated
    - Diaries, 1890-1896 (Box 188, Folder 5923-5929)
    - Diaries, 1900 (Box 189, Folder 5930)
    - School exercises and notebooks, undated (Box 189, Folder 5931-5938)
    - Wedding souvenirs, 1894 (Box 189, Folder 5939-5940)
    - Writings and notes, undated (Box 190, Folder 5941-5966)
  - Smith, Edward North, papers, 1898, 1937-1940, undated (Box 191, Folder 5967-5975)
  - Smith, Olive Cary Macdonald, papers, circa 1923, undated (Box 191, Folder 5976-5978)
  - Correspondence, 1874-1960
    - Micklejohn, Helen to Clark, Paul and Alice, 1961-1962 (Box 192, Folder 5979)
    - Powers, Ike P. to Powers, Lorinda L., undated (Box 192, Folder 5980)
    - Powers, Lorinda L., miscellaneous, 1899-1919 (Box 192, Folder 5981-5983)
    - Smith, Alice Lamon Powers, miscellaneous, 1874-1906, undated (Box 192, Folder 5984-5996)
    - Smith, Edward North, 1886-1939
      - Crossman, Edgar, 1938-1939 (Box 193, Folder 5997-5998)
      - To Smith, Alice Lamon Powers, 1886-1899 (Box 193, Folder 5999-6009)
      - To Smith, Hannibal, 1886-1890 (Box 194, Folder 6010-6018)
      - Miscellaneous, 1893-1926 (Box 194, Folder 6019-6020)
    - Smith, Eunice, 1965 (Box 194, Folder 6021)
    - Smith, Marion Ward, 1939-1960, undated (Box 194, Folder 6022)
    - Young, Mary Louisa to Powers Household, 1893 June 27 (Box 194, Folder 6023)
- Subject Files and Printed Material, circa 1920s-1960s, undated; Series V; 8.5; (21 boxes)
  This series contains printed ephemera, pamphlets, and clippings collected by Smith to document his work, as background research for writing projects, and for personal interest. The clippings include reviews of his work and his own letters to editors.
  Arranged by subject.
  - Clippings of publicity, reviews, and letters to editors, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 195, Folder 6024-6033)
    Also stored in: Oversize.
    See also: Scrapbooks
  - Clippings of publicity, reviews, and letters to editors, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 196, Folder 6034-6048)
  - Distributist-Agrarian Movement, undated (Box 197, Folder 6049-6104)
  - Free America; a magazine to promote independence, 1937-1944 (Box 197, Folder 6105)
  - National Mental Health Act, undated (Box 198, Folder 6106-6123)
  - Society of Friends, undated (Box 199, Folder 6124-6179)
  - Society of Friends, undated (Box 200, Folder 6180-6260)
  - Society of Friends, undated (Box 201, Folder 6261-6322)
  - Society of Friends, undated (Box 202, Folder 6323-6396)
  - YWCA, undated (Box 203, Folder 6397-6425)
  - Miscellaneous printed material and ephemera, undated (Box 204–207)
  - Miscellaneous printed and manuscript material (Box 224)
    Includes pencil sketch of E.A. Robinson
  - Outline Map of U.S.A., New England Settlement 1660-1900, colored map, 66" x 46" (Box 226 (Roll))
  - Volumes, undated (Box 208–213)
    Includes seven books annotated by CPS, and five inscribed by Edward N. Smith.
  - Volumes (Box A)
    Annotated and interleaved with notes by CPS
  - Volumes (Box B)
  - Volumes (Box C)
  - Volumes (Box D)
  - Volumes (Box E)
- Photographs, circa 1870s-1960s; Series VI; 2; (3 boxes)
  Series VI. Photographs includes portraits and snapshots of Smith throughout his life, as well as images of his family members and a few of friends and schoolmates. Images of his parents and grandparents include portraits and school photographs from the late nineteenth century. A few World War I images are present, showing soldiers and Olive Macdonald as a nurse, as are some images of Smith in Europe in the 1920s with friends including Bernardine Szold and Monroe Wheeler. The series also includes an album of photographs of the mill at Sackets Harbor, New York, by Prentiss Taylor, with related correspondence. Images related to Smith's writings, including reproduction photographs of Edwin Arlington Robinson, are also present. A few additional photographs can be found in the scrapbooks in Series III. Personal Papers.
  - Smith, Chard Powers, undated (Box 214, Folder 6426-6465)
  - Family and friends, undated (Box 215, Folder 6466-6555)
  - Family and friends, undated (Box 216, Folder 6556-6561)
- Oversize, 1; (7 boxes)
  - Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976 (in Series I. Correspondence), 1926 December 21 (Box 217, Folder 6562)
  - Ladies Day, proofs (in Series II. Writings), undated (Box 218, Folder 6563)
  - Poets of the Twenties, proofs (in Series II. Writings), undated (Box 218, Folder 6564)
  - Prelude to Man, notes and drafts (in Series II. Writings), undated (Box 219, Folder 6565)
  - Prelude to Man, proofs (in Series II. Writings), undated (Box 219, Folder 6566-6567)
  - Photostat copies of topographical maps of Gettysburg Battlefield, 1863, with mailing tube (in Series III. Personal Papers), 1960 (Box 217, Folder 6568)
  - Clippings of publicity, reviews, and letters to editors (in Series V. Subject Files and Printed Material), circa 1920s-1960s (Box 220, Folder 6569-6586)
  - Photographs (in Series VI. Photographs), undated (Box 221, Folder 6587-6603)
  - Photographs (in Series VI. Photographs), undated (Box 222, Folder 6604-6612)
  - Scrapbook pages related to undergraduate activities at Yale (in Series III. Personal Papers), 1913-1916 (Box 223, Folder 6613)
  - Army General Staff College certificate (in Series III. Personal Papers), 1918 (Box 223, Folder 6614)
  - Photograph of "Olive and Janet" ((in Series VI. Photographs), undated (Box 223, Folder 6615)
  - Miscellaneous printed material and clippings (in Series V. Subject Files and Printed Material), 1910-1977, undated (Box 223, Folder 6616-6617)
  - Miscellaneous printed and manuscript material (in Series V. Subject Files and Printed Material), 1902-1940 (Box 225)
    Includes pencil sketch of Chard Powers Smith, 1940.
- Restricted Fragile Materials
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 16, folder 620, undated (Box CS)